-==www.RagBear.com==- 是, 首相  第2季第3集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=- 翻译&校对&时间轴: Tpring
外交事件
汉弗莱 我们得谈谈海峡隧道
Humphrey, we've got to discuss this ceremony for
奠基典礼宣传的事      好的
the start of work on the Channel Tunnel.
外交部又在拖延了
The Foreign Office is stalling.
他们说协议条文还没敲定呢
They say things still haven't been finalised.
也该完了 头等大事啊
About time they were. Big occasion.
大门揭幕 尊敬的首相吉姆哈克亲手奠基
the laying of the foundation stone by the PM, James Hacker.
"我们两大民主国家世代相连"(丘吉尔)
This historic link between our two great sovereign democracies.
重大新闻      可外交部
Great coverage. F.O.
还没和法国谈妥呢
Haven't agreed everything with the French.
对 我看唯一办法
The only solution is for me to
只有找法国总统作高峰会谈
have a meeting with the French president
由我亲自商定了
and sort it out myself.
我真没想到 您在考虑如此激进的手段
I didn't know you were considering such a stimulating approach.
我想好了
Well, I am.
首相 您觉得您个人有能力与法国谈判吗?
Are you capable of concluding this negotiation?
有什么难的 关键分歧在哪?
What are the outstanding points?
他们主要担心主权问题
Mainly they're concerned with sovereignty.
您认为边界应该在哪?
Where do you believe the frontier should be?
边界?      英国和法国的边界
The frontier between Britain and France.
现在的位置有什么不好?
What's wrong with wherever it is now?
领海界限各三海里 隧道中央归谁?
The three-mile limit. Who would own the middle of the tunnel?
您看 英国的立场是一边一半
The British position is that we should own half each.
挺公平啊      对 可法国人不觉得公平
That seems fair. The French don't think it's fair.
他们希望边界设在多佛港(英国)
They want the frontier to be at Dover.
岂有此理
Ridiculous.
列车的主权又归谁?
Who would have sovereignty over the trains?
如果法国列车上发生罪案
If a crime was committed on a French train
在英国地段 司法权归英国还是法国?
in the British sector, who'd have jurisdiction?
英国...不 法国...不 英国
The British. Well... No, the French. No, the British.
如果一具尸体从法国地段的
And if a body was pushed out of
英国列车里抛出呢?
a British train in the French sector?
法国吧 不 英国 嗯...
Well, the French. Um... no, the British. Um...
如果一台英国卡车装上
If a British lorry was loaded onto
英国地段的法国列车 归谁管呢?
a French train in the British sector?
英国卡车 归英国...或者法国
A British lorry, the British... or the French.
能不能把刑事司法权分成两支
Could jurisdiction be divided into two legs?
内外各一支?
Home and away?
对 谢谢 伯纳
Yes, thank you, Bernard.
隧道中央要立界碑吗?
Should we have a frontier post in the middle of the tunnel?
要啊 呃 不要      立在半道上?
Well, yeah. Er, no. Halfway across?
海关和移民检查
Should we have customs and immigration clearance
设在这边还是那边 还是两边都要?
at one end or the other or both ends?
恕我直言 汉弗莱 这都是律师的事
With respect, these are points for the lawyers to discuss.
正是 首相 可我好像听说您要亲自解决
Precisely, but I thought you wanted to handle it yourself.
当然 我没打算讨论国际法的细枝末节
I don't want to discuss points of abstruse international law.
我是想敲定政治问题
I want to get the political points settled.
原来主权不是政治问题啊
So sovereignty's not political?
真有意思
How interesting.
还有路标 法国希望法语在前 英语在后
The French want the signs to be in French first and English second.
那可不行      那您就开不成庆典了
No! Then you can't have your ceremony.
不如法国那边法语在前 英国英语在前?
Well, French first at the French end?
列车上呢?      得了 汉弗莱 这重要吗?
What about on the trains? Oh, does it matter?
法国人觉得重要 菜单呢 法语还是英语?
And the menus? French or English?
不能半途上换一套吗?
Couldn't they be changed halfway?
不行 法国人最顽固不化
No. The French are adamant.
所以英法两国协和式飞机
That is why the British and French Concorde are
都写成法语 末尾有个E
spelt the French way with an E.
我们就没压倒过法国吗?      也有几次
Don't we ever get our way with the French? Sometimes.
最近一次是几时?      滑铁卢战役 1815年
When was the last time? Battle of Waterloo, 1815.
当然 法国人可能还会提到劫车问题      劫车?
The French may raise the question of hijacking. Hijacking?
要是恐怖分子劫持列车
What if terrorists hijacked the train and
威胁要炸掉隧道 怎么办?
threatened to blow up the tunnel?
这个让给法国管吧 让他们头疼好了
Give the French jurisdiction over the lot, then it's their problem.
您看 首相 要是您主持谈判
If you'd handled the negotiations,
您会把什么都让给法国的
you'd have just handed everything over to the French.
不过我以为 法国会耍些下流花招
I personally believe the French will come up with a
来占取主动
totally underhand ploy to gain the advantage.
不过您当然早算到了 首相
But no doubt you've anticipated that.
仔细想想 谈判也没必要由我亲自主持吧
I don't think it's necessary for me to conduct these negotiations.
如果非要丧权辱国 交给外交大臣好了
If humiliating concessions have to be made, let the FS make them.
真英明 首相      来杯雪利酒吧 伯纳
Very wise. Let's have a glass of sherry, Bernard.
首相 能谈谈您前任回忆录的问题了吗?
May we discuss the vexed question of your predecessor's memoirs?
老天 又怎么啦?      貌似最末一章
What now? The final chapter
写的是他的辞职和您继任的经过
concerns his resignation and your accession to the premiership.
因此他想查阅某些政府文件
He wants access to certain papers.
不能封杀这本胡忆录吗?
Can't we stop these bloody memoirs?
唉 回忆录是种职业病
Memoirs, alas, are an occupational hazard.
最可恨的是他的背叛
It's the betrayal that upsets me.
读到头7章之前 我还当他是朋友呢
Until I'd read the first seven chapters, I thought he was a friend.
他怎么能那样说我      哪样?
He says some shocking things. Such as?
他管我叫两面派      太不合适了
He calls me two-faced. That was very wrong.
你承认这不合适?      当然了 干杯
You admit he was wrong? Yes, indeed. Cheers.
毫无保密意识      保密意识?
Unforgivably indiscreet. indiscreet?
哦 也不合适      他怎能这样诽谤我?
Oh, and wrong. How can he tell such lies about me?
什么诽谤? 哦 明白了
What lies? Oh, yes, I see.
他能落什么好?
What's in it for him?
打开销路?      不是这个问题
Bestseller? No, it's not that.
他撒谎不是为利益 是天性使然
He lies because it's in his nature.
他阴险 恶毒 卑鄙无耻
He's treacherous, malevolent... and vile.
要是他还想要什么爵位
If he thinks he'll get any more honours or
公营机构或者王室职位 做梦去吧
quango, he's got another thing coming.
有我在 他休想再沽名钓誉
He's not getting one ounce more recognition!
对 这事重要吗? 因为...
Yes. Look, is this important? Because...
不会吧 哦
No? Oh.
途中去世的? 知道了 谢谢
He was dead on arrival? I see. Thanks.
坏消息 伯纳?      是也不是
Bad news, Bernard? Yes... and no.
您的前任 大不列颠帝国前首相
Your predecessor, the previous Prime Minster of Great Britain,
刚才突发心脏病去世了
has just died of a heart attack.
悲剧啊      悲剧悲剧
Tragic. Tragic.
他是位伟人      伟人伟人
He was a great man. Great man.
他会永垂不朽的      永垂不朽
He'll be sorely missed. Sorely missed.
他的回忆录也是      永远完不成了
So will his memoirs. Which will never be finished.
唉      唉
Alas. Alas.
似乎在临终前 他说希望以国礼下葬
he expressed a hope that he might have a state funeral.
不过既然您不想让他沽名钓誉...
But in view of your wish to pay him no...
不 伯纳 不 你误会我了
No, you must have misunderstood me.
我相信会有很多人想给他送葬的
Many people will want to attend his funeral.
来向一位伟大首相致敬
To pay tribute to a great Prime Minister?
对...
Yeah...
顺便确认他真的死了
...and to make sure he's dead.
7名英联邦首相 美国副总统
Seven Commonwealth Prime Ministers, the American Vice President,
俄国外交部长 6名欧洲各国首相
six European Prime Ministers.
真不错      非常不错 首相
Pretty good. Very good, Prime Minister.
我是东道主      正是这样
I am the host. Yes, indeed.
各国领袖簇拥 世界舞台中央
Amongst all the world's leaders, centre of the world stage.
庄重又不失尊严 强忍悲痛      可不是
Bearing your grief with dignity and fortitude. Quite.
庄重的悲痛很能刺激支持率
Dignified grief goes down very well with the voters,
尤其在全世界政治家烘托之下
especially when it's shared by world statesmen.
死亡真是一件盛事
It's a wonderful thing, death.
让大家同心同德 法国总理又有什么事?
What's this query against the French Prime Minister?
我想法国大使马上会来跟您谈
The French ambassador's coming to see you.
会全方位多角度拍摄吧?      是啊
Plenty of room for TV cameras.
10号门口 沿途夹道 修道院里里外外
Outside No.10, outside the abbey, inside the abbey.
安排一台正对着我的座位
One pointing directly at my pew.
那摄影师不就得站在布道坛里吗?
Um... wouldn't that mean putting the cameraman in the pulpit?
没问题的吧?
Will that be all right?
那大主教就有点站不开了
It won't leave a lot of room for the Archbishop.
他要从哪里布道?
Well... So where will he preach from?
貌似他得站在布道坛里      那我的摄影机摆哪里?
He'll need to be in the pulpit. Where will my camera be?
倒还有个主祭台
There's always the high altar,
不过估计大主教也要用的
but I think the Archbishop may need that as well.
他以为他是谁啊?
Who does he think he is?
他大概以为这是宗教仪式
He thinks it's a religious ceremony.
没人告诉他这是政党聚会
Nobody's told him it's a party political.
伯纳 法国大使来了吧?
The French ambassador here, is he?
他马上到 可我能先说句话吗?
Yes, but could I have a word first?
法国首相不来了 换法国总统来
The French PM isn't coming. The President's coming instead.
总统? 太棒了      不 首相 糟糕透了
President? Marvellous! No, it's terrible!
怎么?      女王3年前访法时
When the Queen visited France,
送过总统一条拉布拉多狗
she presented him with a Labrador puppy.
现在它生小狗了 他要回赠一条      不
Now he's bringing her one of its puppies. No!
恐怕是真的      我说吧
Afraid so. I knew it!
怎么了 这不是向我们示好吗?
It seems to be rather a nice gesture.
是示意 不过不是示好
It's a gesture, but hardly a nice one.
怎么讲?      女王必须拒绝
Why not? She'll have to refuse it.
为什么?      隔离检疫啊 首相
Why? Quarantine!
狗不能随便进口
You can't import dogs!
必须在机场隔离检疫6个月
It'll have to spend six months in quarantine.
老天 法国人会理解的 对吧?
The French will understand, won't they?
他们私下里理解 所以才耍这花招
They'll understand it privately,
可他们官方拒绝理解
but they'll refuse to understand it officially.
外交部得想想办法 去找彼得      是
The Foreign Office must sort it out. Get Peter.
汉弗莱 他们想引发外交事件
Humphrey, they're creating a diplomatic incident
好夺取海峡隧道的主动权
so they can get their own way over the tunnel.
原来如此 首相
Of course, Prime Minister!
彼得 你听说了吧?      对 首相
Peter, you've heard the news? Yes.
我们怎么办?      我不知道
What are we going to do? I don't know.
你是我的外交部长啊
You're my Foreign Affairs Secretary.
对 我们在想办法变通 可检疫归内政部管
Yes, but the Home Office is responsible for quarantine.
去找格拉汉 不能让他们收回礼物吗?
Get Graham. Can't you get them to withdraw this gift?
我们都试过了 提议改成狗的画像
We've suggested a painting of the puppy,
铜像 瓷像 全都碰了壁
a bronze, a porcelain model. Not a hope.
不能让他们填起来吗?      什么...
Couldn't you get them to stuff it? Well...
哦 做成标本 不行 没戏
Oh, taxidermy. No, no chance.
格拉汉 内政部得想办法
Tell the Home Office they
绕过检疫规章
must find a way round quarantine regulations.
恐怕办不到 首相      为什么?
Out of the question. What do you mean?
首先这条规章我们对一切国民
We enforce them vigorously with all British citizens
和世界各国都不通融
and foreign nationals.
再说检疫法是女王亲笔签署的
Also the Quarantine Act is signed by the Queen.
她不能专对自己法外开恩啊 办不到
She can't be the only one to break her own laws.
法国大使来了 首相      要他先等一会
The French ambassador's here. Ask him to wait for a moment.
回外交部去 叫他们和内政部商量
Get back to the Foreign Office.
必须想办法变通
Say we've got to find a way round this.
你们都跟伯纳保持联络 伯纳 你联络皇宫
Keep in touch with Bernard.
汉弗莱 你找法务部 统筹协调 好吗?
Bernard, liaise with the palace. Humphrey, coordinate it all.
我会在内阁办公室设个通讯室
I'll set up an operations room.
我们还得做什么?
Anything else we ought to do?
我想您该见法国大使了 首相
I think you should see the ambassador now.
好 叫他进来
OK, wheel him in.
不许走 汉弗莱 留下给我打气
Don't you go, Humphrey!
要我准备文件吗?
Do I need any papers?
不用 准备海绵绷带就好
No, just a sponge and a towel.
法国大使阁下到      大使阁下
His Excellency, the French ambassador. Excellency.
首相 多谢您拨冗与我会晤
You're most kind to give me your time.
(法语)万分荣幸
Enchant?
听说您急着要敲定海峡隧道协议?
You're anxious to finalise the agreement for the tunnel?
可不是 老实说...
Very much so. In fact...
也不算急 当然如果...      当然
There's no real hurry. It would be nice if... Quite.
我国政府认为 如果我们借这次葬礼...
My government feels that if we took advantage of the funeral...
我个人谨表哀悼 悲剧啊      悲剧悲剧
My condolences, by the way. A tragic loss. Oh, tragic, tragic.
如果我们借这次葬礼
If we took advantage of the funeral
让您和我国总统面谈...
for you and our President to speak...
对 当然 不过还有好多
Of course, I will be host to a
重要人物出席 我不太好安排
large number of distinguished people. It may not be easy.
您不想和我们总统谈话?
You do not wish to speak to our President?
不不不 当然...想也不想
Oh, yes, yes, yes, of course. Well, yes... and no.
谈话当然可以 不过谈判...
Speak, yes, of course, but negotiate...
您不觉得这种友邻之争
Don't you think these quarrels between friends
最好由当面对话解决吗?
are best resolved by just talking together?
友邻之间 没错
Between friends, yes.
不然总统可要伤心了
Otherwise the President may be hurt.
个人倒没什么 可他是代表全法国受辱
Not personally, but as a snub to France.
不不 绝无此意 我们是世交好友
No intention. Great friends.
太好了 第二个问题是访问期间使团的安全
The second point is the security of our embassy during the visit.
对 警察厅长说都安排妥了
Yes, everything's in hand.
我国政府要求批准法国警方随团护卫
requests that the French police be permitted to guard
法国警方? 怎么可能
French police? No, that's not possible.
也不一定不可能吧
It is surely not impossible?
你们不信任英国警方吗?
Don't you trust the British police?
我国政府对英国警方不做评价
We make no comment on the British police.
但我们总统更希望让法国警方来管
But our President want the French police were in charge.
您看 阁下 问题是
The problem, Excellency, is that
届时会有一百多个使团来到伦敦
there are well over a hundred embassies in London.
大家当然都想用自己的警察
No doubt they'd all want their own police.
大多数警察会带机关枪
Most of them would carry machine guns.
女皇政府并不完全相信...
Her Majesty's government is not... totally convinced
这会让伦敦更加安全
that that would make London a safer place.
那我国政府要大失所望了
My government will be most disappointed.
好在我还有件愉快的事
But now I can turn to a happy matter.
我国总统会带来一件小礼物 赠给女皇陛下
Our President will be bringing a little present to Her Majesty.
真周到      一条小狗
How charming. A little puppy.
她名叫"小砂锅"
Her name is Cocotte.
"小砂锅"
Cocotte.
生它的那条拉布拉多犬正是
She comes from the litter of the same Labrador that
女王上次访法时
Her Majesty presented to the President
慷慨赠给总统的
on her last state visit to France.
可以通报他赠送仪式的安排吗?
Let him know the arrangements for the presentation.
当然 你们太周到了
Oh, delightful thought.
可惜赠送仪式6个月内不能举行
The presentation won't be possible for another six months.
我国检疫法的规定      岂有此理
Our quarantine laws. Absurd.
贵国女王来访时带了条狗
Your Queen gave her dog during her visit.
为什么我国总统就不行?
Why can our President not do the same?
对 承蒙好意 我们其实非常...
Delightful thought, nothing we'd rather...
不过国有国法
but the law is the law.
法律当然是防范带病动物的吧?      对...
Surely it exists to exclude infected animals? Er... yes.
您是暗示法国总统会向英国女王赠送
Do you suggest the President of France would present
一条病狗?
with a diseased puppy?
不不不...      那就这么定了
No, no, no... Then it is settled.
不 不能定 恐怕您必须
No, it is not. Suggest to your
建议总统换别的礼物
President that he brings a different gift.
办不到 要说总统本人 还有希望
Out of the question. Were it the President alone, perhaps.
但总统夫人 我国第一夫人决意要送
The President's wife, our first lady, has set her heart on it.
她已经认准了
She is determined.
我们会尽力而为 不过恐怕无能为力
We'll make every effort, but it may not be possible.
首相 我国政府将感到莫名惊诧和严重受辱
I cannot tell you the gravity my government would feel
如果女王陛下居然拒收她本人
if Her Majesty were to refuse a gift in exchange
赠给总统礼物的回礼
for the one our President accepted from her.
恐怕这不仅会被看作有辱国体
I fear it would be interpreted as both a national
更会冒犯总统个人及其夫人
and a personal affront to the President and his wife.
阁下 您得劝总统别带那条母狗来
you must ask the President not to bring that bitch with him.
不不 那条小狗
No, no, the puppy.
我是说小狗
I meant the puppy.
还得单独安排夫人们的行程
We have to lay on visits for the wives.
外交部喜欢这样 好把她们全撇开
The Foreign Office like it. Keeps them out of the way.
干吗不让她们陪同丈夫?      丈夫忙着呢
Why can't they be with their husbands? They're busy.
只是葬礼上罢了      安妮 他们不是来送葬的
Only at the funeral. They're not coming for the funeral.
是来谈政务的 这是一次工作葬礼
They're coming here for the politics. This is a working funeral.
上回挪威的国葬 法国 德国和我都忙着
At that funeral in Norway, the French, Germans and I,
谈进出口配额问题 连教堂都忘去了
talking about quotas, we forgot to go to the cathedral.
他们发现了吗?
Did they notice?
能没发现嘛 我们都迟到了
They noticed, all right. We got there late.
保安背了黑锅 如今什么都能怪保安人员
Blamed security. You can blame security for anything nowadays.
那这次葬礼可以算首脑峰会了?
So this funeral will be a sort of summit.
对 这是天赐良机
Yes. It's a heaven-sent opportunity.
字面上的      对
Literally. Yes.
比峰会还好 没有既定目标
Better than a summit because there are no expectations.
没人指望领导人从葬礼上搞到
People don't expect leaders to come back with
禁止核试验或者生产限额协定
test-ban agreements or quota reductions,
于是我们就能谈些有意义的东西了
so we can have some meaningful discussions.
峰会只算是公关大会
A summit is just a public-relations circus.
就没人是来向老朋友致敬的吗?
Isn't anyone coming to pay tribute to a friend?
朋友? 要是只请他的朋友
A friend? If only his friends came to the abbey,
连小礼拜堂都填不满
we wouldn't even fill the vestry.
他这一死为世界做的贡献
He's done much more for the world by dying
比他活着一辈子都大
than he ever did in the whole of his life.
你敲定仪式细节了吗?
Have you agreed the service?
对 一直奏乐      这倒不错
Yeah, lots of music. That's nice.
嗯 有管风琴掩护 就能谈点有用的了
Mm, you can have useful discussions when the organ's playing.
齐声祷告时就不行      布道的时候呢?
Have to shut up for the lesson. What about the sermon?
那是用来倒时差的
That's when you catch up on jet lag.
没错 这葬礼来得正是时候
This funeral's come at the right moment.
有一堆事要谈呢 北约 华沙条约 中东问题
We've all sorts to discuss about NATO, the Warsaw Pact
要是这三天解决不完呢?
And what if you don't sort it all out?
那我们只能盼望
We'll just have to hope that before too long
有别的大人物尽快蹬腿了
somebody else important snuffs it.
对 我跟内政部谈过了
I've spoken to the Home Office.
他们说没理由要求国会为该狗专门立法
there's no grounds to pass an act to for this dog
我知道特许授权法什么都能授权
I know an enabling act can enable anything,
不过首相觉得
but the PM feels it
这只能授权他输掉下次大选
would merely enable him to lose the next election.
伯纳 能不能考虑把整个皇宫
Have you thought of turning Buckingham Palace
变成犬只隔离区?      你说真的?
into a quarantine zone for dogs?
只是个想法罢了
Just a thought.
女王的威尔士矮脚狗呢?
What about the corgis?
稍等 格拉汉 联络皇宫
Hang on. Graham, check with the palace
确认女王没有正式得知礼物的事
that Her Majesty's not been told officially
免得拒收和她扯上关系
this gift then she can't be implicated in refusing it.
对 我们需要同声传译
Yes, we will want simultaneous translators.
不 会见英语国家元首时就免了
not when the PM meets the leaders of English nations.
对 英语国家可以包括美国
Yes, they can be said to include the US...
以显示我们的慷慨大度 我得挂了
...with a certain generosity of spirit. Got to go.
对 10国元首专机今天抵达 特工处快疯了
Yes, 10 PMs are flying in today. Special Branch are crazy.
皇家海军乐队也是 得演奏所有的国歌
So is the Royal Marines band who play all the national anthems.
知道了 阿根廷不来了 真走运
I see. Argentina's not coming. A bit of luck.
因为马岛事件?
Because of the Falklands?
不 因为他们的国歌有6分钟长
No, because their anthem goes on for about six minutes.
喂 我知道你担心狗的事 我也是
I know you're worried about this dog. So am I.
跟我们驻巴黎大使说说
Talk to our ambassador in Paris.
看他能不能想法灭了它
See if he can think of a way to nobble it.
你知道 下点药什么的
You know, slip it something.
问问保加利亚人
See if the Bulgarians have
还有没有毒伞尖 (乔治马可夫案 1978)
got any spare umbrella tips.
伯纳 还有个办法
If we made the palace an extension
把皇宫并入法国大使馆 狗就不算入境了
of the French embassy, the dog would be on foreign territory.
彼得 首相正拼命争取海峡隧道的主权
The PM is fighting for the sovereignty of the tunnel.
把皇宫都让出去他会怎么想?
How would he feel about palace sovereignty?
你觉得皇室会怎么想? 喂
How do you think the sovereign would feel?
不 礼堂里不能按字母顺序排位
No, we can't have alphabetical seating in the abbey.
不然伊拉克会挨着伊朗坐
You'd have Iraq and Iran next to each other.
以色列和约旦也坐同一排
Plus Israel and Jordan all sitting in the same pew.
我们会引发第三次世界大战的
We'd be in danger of starting World War III.
我知道爱尔兰也是I开头 可爱尔兰没用
I know Ireland begins with an I, but it doesn't make it any better.
爱尔兰在任何事上都不起作用
Ireland doesn't make anything any better.
对了 传达所有人
If the papal envoy says,
要是教皇特使说"本座要净手"
"We desire to wash our hands",
就是说他要上厕所
it means he wants a pee.
对 "本座"是尊称 坐的是皇家宝厕(同花顺)
Yes, a royal "we", followed by a royal flush.
小心提防南非人
Watch out for the South Africans.
人权问题?      不 他们想倾销柚子
human rights? No, they're trying to unload grapefruit.
伯纳 皇宫问红毡铺地会不会有问题
The palace wants to know about the red carpets.
女王担心象牙海岸(非洲)总统
The Ivory Coast wishes to award Her Majesty
想向女王赠送大象勋章
with the Order of the Elephant.
别挂 格拉汉 不能再扯进什么动物了
Hang on. We can't have another animal,
尤其是大象
especially an elephant.
白厅 内政部 外交部和卫生部
Whitehall, the Home Office, Foreign Office, the DHSS,
都为一条小狗头疼一周了
have been tied up with one puppy for nearly a week!
政府都瘫痪了 不许要大象
No elephants!
不 塞浦路斯大主教不叫至圣宗座
The mode of address to a Cypriot archbishop is not Your Ecstasy,
叫至福圣座
it's Your Beatitude.
老天爷 又搞什么...
For God's sake, what is it...
哦 抱歉 首相 我马上来
Oh, sorry, Prime Minister. I'll come in straight away.
这是什么 伯纳?      海峡隧道的档案 首相
What on earth is that? The Channel Tunnel file.
不 那一本呢?      小狗的档案
No, no, the other one. That's the puppy file.
大致怎么说?      重量是3.5磅
Where have we got to? It weighed in at three and a half pounds.
小狗?      不 档案
The puppy? No, the file.
怎么回事?      眼下我们已照会法国
What's happening? We've told the French
说机场保安不得不
that airport security will have to
把狗留在机场检疫
keep the puppy in quarantine.
他们怎么说?      还没回复
What do they say? No reply yet.
我们还指出
It is on the route
机场在皇宫去温莎城堡途中
from the palace to Windsor,
女王可以顺便去看看它
so the Queen could visit it.
隔离中的狗能看吗?      如果不行
Can you visit quarantined dogs? Well, if she can't,
她可以从车上朝它挥挥手吧
she can sort of wave to it.
你说他们会作何反应?
What do you think they'll do?
我想他们会威胁爆给媒体
Threaten to publish the story
除非我们在海峡隧道上让步
if we don't give in on the tunnel.
首相 我有紧急消息      希望是好消息
I have urgent news. I hope it's good news.
是也不是 警方在法国使馆区发现了炸弹
Yes and no. The police found a bomb in the French embassy grounds.
什么? 谁放的?      还不知道
What?! Who put it there? We don't know yet.
很多人都有动机      我就算一个
Lots of people could have a motive. Me, for a start.
幸好被我们找到了...是好事吧
It's a good thing we found it... I suppose.
另一条消息更糟 法国总统不飞过来了
The President is not flying in for the funeral.
太好了      他不坐飞机 改坐车了 秘密入境
That's marvellous! He's not flying, he's driving! Secretly!
拿专机作安全掩护      好主意
The plane is just going to be a decoy. Good idea.
绝妙的主意 他可以带狗进来了      不行
A brilliant idea! He can bring the puppy! No!
首相 您要授权把总统专车拦下搜查吗?
give permission for his car to be stopped and searched?
您难道要侵犯他们的外交豁免权
Will you violate their diplomatic immunity and
搜查外交邮袋?
search the diplomatic bag?
他们总不能把狗藏袋子里吧
Even they wouldn't put a puppy in a bag.
会变成狗食袋(餐馆打包袋)
It'd be a doggy bag.
要是真搜出来 那可捅马蜂窝了
If we found it, that'd put the cat among the pigeons.
纵狗出袋了
Let the dog out of the bag.
对 可是首相 万一车里没有狗呢?
But just suppose it wasn't there?
对 我不能冒这个险
Yeah. I can't take the risk.
可如果狗在里面
If it was there,
他们就可以开进法国大使馆
they'll drive into the French embassy
狗就进入了法国领土 在伦敦正中央
and that puppy will be on French territory here
悬在我们头顶上      希望它懂规矩吧
Hanging over our heads. Better pray it's house-trained.
首相 真抱歉 能失陪一下吗?
I'm so sorry, would you excuse the Prime Minister?
首相 我们有麻烦了
We have a problem.
您跟法国总统说上话了吗?
Have you spoken to the French President yet?
就说了几句套话      具体是什么?
A couple of well-chosen words. What, precisely?
就是"您好"(法语)
Bonsoir, actually.
首相 您不能不理他
You can't put it off.
不然他又多一个被冒犯的借口了
It'll be one more thing for him to take offence at.
他没这么容易被冒犯吧?
He can't be that easily offended, can he?
当然没有 不过据我们所知
No, but in exchange
要想让他们放弃狗的事
for dropping this dog nonsense,
他们想要全部隧道主权 从3海里领海算起
they want sovereignty over the tunnel from the three-mile limit.
岂有此理      这是谈判开价
Absurd. That's the negotiating position.
实际上他们同意五五开 从中间算
They'll concede to a 50-50 split midway across the Channel
只要我们同意用法语作第一语言
if we agree to French as the first language on all
路标 告示 菜单 所有东西
signs, information, menus, everything.
都先法后英      我非得让步吗?
French comes before English. Must I concede?
如果您想要奠基礼的话      好吧 他在哪?
If you want your foundation-stone ceremony. All right. Where is he?
哈克夫人 您见过联合国
Mrs Hacker, have you met
教科文组织的贝林杰先生了吗?
Monsieur Berenger from UNESCO?
幸会       夫人 葬礼太棒了
Such a good funeral.
比安德罗波夫(苏共书记)的强多了
Much better than Andropov's.
他们太郁闷了      您喜欢就好
That was gloomy. So glad you're enjoying it.
首相 有空吗?      这位是美国副总统
Prime Minister, got a minute? The American Vice President.
哦 副总统先生      我刚跟苏联人聊完
I was talking to the Soviets.
葛罗米柯的波兰笑话太好笑了
Gromyko's got a great Polish joke.
什么这么好笑?      雅鲁泽尔斯基(波兰总统)
What is it? Jaruzelski!
警察厅长 这位是联合国教科文的贝林杰先生
can I introduce you to Monsieur Berenger from UNESCO?
教科文? 对对 不错的小国家
UNESCO? Ah, yes. Gallant little country.
汉弗莱爵士      您记得苏联大使吧
Ah, Sir Humphrey! You remember the Soviet ambassador.
我说 前首相的去世真让人痛心
the death of the past PM is a very sad occasion.
对对 真痛心      可也不算英国的损失
Oh, yes, yes, very sad... But it is no loss for Britain.
你知道他的问题在哪吗?
You know what his trouble was?
他这里很厉害 这里很厉害...
He had plenty here, plenty here...
可是这里不行
...but nothing here!
什么 伯纳?
Yes, Bernard?
失陪了 副总统先生
Forgive me,
我要去找法国朋友聊聊了
I must talk to our French friends.
好 可我得跟您谈谈
I did want to talk to you about the
北约的德国基地的事
NATO bases in Germany.
明天修道院里谈      一言为定
Tomorrow, Westminster Abbey. You got a deal.
首相 您得看看这份安全档案
You need to see this security file.
回头再说 伯纳 我要跟法国总统谈话了
I'm about to talk to the President.
对 可您应该先看这份档案
You should see this file first.
首相 法国大使馆的炸弹
That bomb in the French embassy
是法国警方安放的
was planted by the French police.
开玩笑吧? 为什么?
You're not serious? Why?
为了试我们 证明我们保安不力
To catch us out, prove our security inefficient.
非法偷运炸弹进入英国?
Smuggling explosives into the UK?
正是      有证据吗?
Correct. Got proof?
在他们旅馆找到了配套的雷管 他们招了
We found a detonator in their hotel.
太好了
This is wonderful!
汉弗莱 我先跟总统谈两分钟
Give me two minutes alone with the President.
看我打手势 就送档案进来
When I give you a signal, bring that file in.
首相 用什么手势?
What will the signal be?
万分抱歉 总统先生 我保证他马上就到
I'm so sorry, Monsieur le President. I'm sure he's just coming.
总统先生...海峡隧道的事
Monsieur le President... the tunnel.
隧道 没错 但首先 能不能先澄清个小误会
can we clear up this misunderstanding about the puppy
关于我明天向女王赠狗的事?
which I am presenting to Her Majesty tomorrow?
据我所知 真对不起
I'm very sorry,
我不能要求女王打破法律
but I can't ask her to break the law.
我没要女王打破法律
I do not want the Queen to break the law
我只要首相给打个折就行
I merely want the PM to bend it.
实在很对不起 我向您郑重道歉
I'm deeply sorry. If I possibly could.
要是法国人民听说了
If the French people learn of this rejection,
这可是照国家脸上打了一耳光...
a national slap in the face...
隧道      隧道? 你给我出难题了
The tunnel. The tunnel? You make it difficult for me.
法国人可不能再挨第二耳光了
The French will not accept a second slap in the face
您还拒绝了我们合情合理的
and you are rejecting our very reasonable proposal
多佛港以外全归法国的建议
for French sovereignty as far as Dover.
不过 这个先不谈
However, setting that to one side,
还有个问题 哪种语言做第一语言?
there is the question of which shall be la langue de preference
汉弗莱爵士 我刚看到明天的典礼安排
Sir Humphrey, I have just seen this order of service for tomorrow.
太让人尴尬了 看这圣歌
It is deeply embarrassing. This hymn.
"施洗者泪洒约旦河岸"(1736)? 怎么啦?
"On Jordan's Bank, The Baptist's Cry"? Why?
您不知道约旦河岸昨天被炸了吗?
Don't you know the Jordan Bank went bust yesterday?
当然 我们可以一半用法语在前
Surely, if we have half the signs in French first
一半用英语...
and half the signs in English...
公平吧?      这不合逻辑
...that's fair? It's not logical.
逻辑重要吗?      法律重要吗?
Does logic matter? Does law matter?
当然 全欧洲就剩英国还...没有狂犬病
Yes. Britain is the only country in Europe still... free of rabies.
真抱歉 伯纳会跟你商量的 伯纳
Bernard will handle this for you. Bernard...
总统先生 打扰一下好吗?
Monsieur le President, will you forgive me?
首相 请您赶紧看看这个
Prime Minister, I think you ought to see this.
不会吧 我不信
No, I don't believe it!
总统先生 我必须请您解释一下
Mr President, I shall have to ask you to explain this.
这件事有多严重 不用我说了吧
I need hardly say how grave this matter is.
首相 请您相信我对此一无所知
Prime Minister, I ask you to believe I had no knowledge of this.
国宾代表团企图陷害我国政府?
An attempt by a guest to deceive our government?
偷运爆炸物进入英国?
Smuggling explosives into the UK?
可您得知道 法国政府从来不知道
You must know that the French government never knows
法国警方在干什么啊
what French security are doing.
您不能为他们负责?      不 我不是这个意思
You can't take responsibility for them? That's not what I mean.
可如果报告属实 请接受我衷心的道歉
If this report is true, accept my profound regrets.
恐怕确实属实      谢谢 首相
It's true enough, I'm afraid. Thank you, Prime Minister.
您看 这下首相就很难处理...
It makes it so difficult for the Prime Minister...
海峡隧道的事了
over the Channel Tunnel.
炸弹的事捅出去 英国人民就不肯让步了
the British will want to make few concessions.
他们不知道能不能安全...通过
They won't know whether it's safe to... go through.
没准里面全是法国官方炸弹      可不是
It could be full of official French bombs. Absolument.
当然 为维护英法两国友谊
Of course, in the interests of Anglo-French friendship,
我们可以忽略你们保安人员的罪行
we could overlook the crimes of your security men.
我说...主权对半分吧?
I suppose... sovereignty halfway across?
我得把这写下来 可以吗
I'll just write that down, if I may.
一半标志先英后法 奠基礼定在两个月后
Half the signs in English first and the ceremony in two months...
在多佛举行
in Dover.
以表达两国间永恒的亲密和信任
As an expression of the trust between our two countries.
我们明天就草拟公报吧 好吗 汉弗莱?
Let us have a draft communiqu?tomorrow.
(法语)是 首相
Mais oui, Prime Minister.
-==www.RagBear.com==- 破烂熊字幕组 欢迎加入